A Guide to the Photographs, Series 1011-1081 FA438
Rockefeller Archive Center
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA), 1946-1968, n.d.; 1027; 6.2 Cubic Feet 19 boxes.
  - Venezuela, 4
    - CBR, Aragua, Agricultural Schools - Escuela-Granja, Escuela Estadal, Cacique Charima, Prints: 16 (Box 9, Folder 163)
      8. Visual education has proved adaptable to most of CBR's community education activity. Elba Velez shows the young staff of the "Cacique Charaima" school how to adapt to their needs. 9. No caption. 10. Opening song of 5-V members at Palo Negro. 11. Dr. J.J. Loreto Jefe of Agricultural Extension Division of MAC, in his opening address at the Achievement Day of Palo Negro 5-V club. 12. Dr. Diego Serpa, Agricultural Agent at Palo Negro accompanying Juan Vicente Gomez Lugo, 14 years old; 5-V club at Palo Negro. 13. Practical farming is taught to youngsters attending the "Escuela-Granja" in Macaro, state of Aragua, one of several organized and in the process of organization by the Venezuelan government to "reclaim" rural youth. 14. Youngsters at the "Escuela-Granja" in Macaro are clearing ground. Even the smallest does his share. 15. There are young farmers and potential farmers studying at the "Escuela-Granja" (farm school) in Macaro, state of Aragua. 16. Worst of all the schools which Ernest Maes, CEV Director, visited in Aragua is this shack at Macuayita. 17. Agricultural students at the "Cacique Charaima" experimental school in Palo Negro provide much of the food for the school lunches. The fine, modern water tower in the background was contributed by the government; behind it is a machinery shed which can be converted into a theater for public performances. 18. Students at the "Cacique Charaima" experimental school in Palo Negro, Aragua, receive courses in agriculture and learn to farm by farming. They also work with a school tractor and various implement attachments. In addition to agriculture, they receive vocational training in shop work. Their sisters are taught sewing, cooking and carpentry, and the same courses are offered to their parents. 19. Children live, work and study at the "Escuela-Granja" (farm school) of Macaro in the state Aragua. The school was visited by Ernest Maes, director of the newly-organized Consejo de Educacion Vocacianal, an AIA program. 20. Construction of useful household objects from waste material - the two girls painting a garbage container made from a discarded oil tin - and household furniture from scrap lumber long has been a part of the CBR home demonstration. 21. Juan B. Acosta lectures on aviary cholera and its control in a class on bee keeping. 22. In this milking shed, students of dairy husbandry learn milking, feeding care, disease control, etc. of dairy cattle. 23. Farmers are laying this canal themselves. They obtained supervised credit loans to buy the material and plant fruit. This is taking place at Agrarian Reform settlement Cachipo, Agagua, Venezuela, 1963.
    - CBR, Aragua, Agricultural Schools - Gonzalito Training Center for Home Farm Agents, Prints: 26 (Box 9, Folder 164)
      24. Guest speaker at the graduation exercises of the Training Center for Farm Home Agents and the Practical School of Agriculture was Dr. Carlos Medina Sanchez, Director of Agriculture for the Ministry of Agriculture. 25. Howard Law, director of CBR and Dr. Carlos Medina Sanchez, Director of Agriculture for the Ministry of Agriculture, join in presenting her diploma to a graduate of the Training Center for Farm Home Agents. 26. Viewing an exhibit prepared by graduating student of the Centro de Capacitacion de Agentes del Hogar Campesino (Training Center for Home Farm Agents) are (left to right) Howard Law, director of the Consejo de Bienstar Rural; Mrs. Arminda Crespo, director of the training center; Dr. Carlos Medina Sanchez, director of Agriculture in the Ministry of Agriculture; and Mrs. Ludmila Prosdocimi, CBR home economics director and consultant at the training center. 27. After a day's work in the practice field, students return to their living quarters by Ministry of Agriculture bus. 28. Students at the Training Center for Farm Home Agents prepare the mixture for fabricating earth-cement blocks for construction. 29. Students learn to make blocks of earth-cement to be used in simple construction as part of their training to become Farm Home Agents. 30. Students learn to make blocks of earth-cement to be used in simple construction as part of their training to become Farm Home Agents. 31. Students at the Training Center for Farm Home Agents learn to make simple, essential pieces of household furniture, such as the chairs they are constructing. 32. A student at the Training Center for Farm Home Agents learns how to construct a garbage can from an old oil can. Proper garbage disposal units, which can be readily and cheaply obtained, are a great need in rural Venezuela. 33. A student at the Training Center for Farm Home Agents learns how to construct a garbage can from an old oil can. Proper garbage disposal units, which can be readily and cheaply obtained, are a great need in rural Venezuela. 34. In one of their farm management courses, the students learn how to care for domestic rabbits in household type hutches. The future Farm Home Agents can then direct farm wives throughout the country in the care of this useful animal. 35. Students of the Training Center for Farm Home Agents in Gonzalito, state of Aragua, are enrolled in all regular home economics courses, such as this sewing class, in addition to carpentry and farm management courses. 36. Home Economist Mrs. Josefina Olivares of the Training Center for Farm Home Agents in Gonzalito, state of Aragua, looks over the platano harvest at the school's practice farm. 37. Mrs. Ludmila Prodocimi, CBR consultant, assists with a classroom demonstration of canning tomato sauce at the Training Center for Farm Home Agents in Gonzalito, state of Aragua. 38. Mrs. Arminda de Crespo, director of the Centro de Capacitacion de Agentes del Hogar Cempesino (Training Center for Farm Home Agents) in Gonzalito, state of Aragua. 39. Mrs. Ludmila Prodocimi, CBR consultant, discusses classroom procedure with a teacher at the Training Center for Farm Home Agents in Gonzalito, state of Aragua. Mrs. Prodocimi is affiliated with the Aragua center as a consultant. 40. Professors of the Training Center for Farm Home Agents learn to use a movie machine as part of the adaptation of visual aids to teaching. 41. This is a typical classroom scene at the Training Center for Farm Home Agents in Gonzalito, state of Aragua. 42. Mrs. Ludmila Prodocimi, CBR consultant, has her office in this building on the school grounds at Gonzalito, state of Aragua. 43. This is a typical classroom scene at the Training Center for Farm Home Agents in Gonzalito, state of Aragua. 44. Students at the Training Center for Farm Home Agents travel by Ministry of Agriculture bus from their classrooms to the practice field. 45. Students at the Training Center for Farm Home Agents select tomatoes for making sauce. 46. Students at the Training Center for Farm Home Agents select tomatoes for making sauce. 47. Mrs. Ludmila Prodocimi, CBR consultant, inspects a stalk of bananas grown on the experimental farm of the Training Center for Farm Home Agents in Gonzalito, state of Aragua. 48. Students at the farm harvest tomatoes under the supervision of Mrs. Ludmila Prodocimi, CBR consultant. 49. Students at the farm harvest tomatoes under the supervision of Mrs. Ludmila Prodocimi, CBR consultant.
    - CBR, Aragua, Agricultural Schools - Providencia - Escuela Practica de Agricultura, Prints: 27 (Box 9, Folder 165)
      50. This is the graduating class picture of students from both the Training Center for Farm Home Agents and the Escuela Practica de Agricultura (Practical School of Agriculture), who received their diplomas in a joint ceremony in Yaracay, capital of the state of Aragua. 51. Howard Law, director of the CBR, congratulates a graduate of the Practical School of Agriculture. 52. A student of the Practical School in Providencia, state of Aragua, performs a vaccination on poultry as a classroom demonstration. 53. Juan B. Acosta, consultant at the Practical School and extension specialist of the CBR joins with a teacher at the school in preparing classroom material. 54. This meeting among teachers of the Practical School in Providencia and CBR staff members took place to discuss a consultant contract between the two groups. Seated at the desk is the director of the school, Dr. Ricardo Araque, at his left CBR's Juan B. Acosta and at his right Ernest Maes, director of the vocational educational program of the American International Association of which CBR is also an affiliate. To the right of Maes is CBR's Dr. Alberto Fernandez. 55. A Ministry of Agriculture bus hauls students at the Practical School of Agriculture to their classes. 56. Professors at the Practical School discuss classroom procedure with CBR consultant Juan B. Acosta. 57. A student at the Practical School learns how to care for rabbits, valuable as small area food animals. 58. A student learns to raise hogs. 59. Professor J. Bolivar conducts a class in agriculture at the Practical School of Agriculture in Providencia, state of Aragua. 60. A student marks the eggs of each hen to determine their fowl production in a course in poultry management at the Practical School. 61. Students learn to vaccinate fowls against Newcastle disease in the poultry management course. 62. Students arrive at CBR center in Palo Negro for a visit. 63. CBR's Juan B. Acosta observes a class determining milk sedimentation. 64. Teachers meet with CBR consultant Juan B. Acosta, third from left; Ernest Maes, vocational education director of the AIA, second from left. Director Ricardo Araque, dean of the school, is fourth from the left. 65. Students climb aboard the Ministry of Agriculture climb bus for a trip to the practice field. 66. Conferring (left to right) are CBR's Juan B. Acosta, Dr. Ricardo Araque, director of the Practical School and CBR's Dr. Alberto Fernandez Yepez. 67. CBR consultant Juan B. Acosta is shown here with one of his classes at the Practical School. 68. In this agriculture class at the Practical School in Providencia, Aragua, students are shown how to open hives properly. 69. This is an aerial view of the agricultural fields. 70. In this milking shed, students of dairy husbandry learn milking, feeding care, disease control, etc. of dairy cattle. 71. A student is learning to control mastitis in dairy cattle. 72. Under the supervision of CBR consultant Juan B. Acosta, a student explains to his fellows the aspects of aviary disease. 73. Foto de una reunion mensual del Club 5-V de San Francisco. Un social ejectua una demonstracion saber injerto de citricas. 74. Andres observa atentamente pasos de una demonstracion de metoda sobre alambrado de colmenai ejectutada par un campenero de Club. 75. El Segundo de Izquierda a derecha es Andes junto alas colmenas construidas para ayudar a companeros de Club en lo proyecto de production de mile. 76. A la derecha de la iota se observe a Andes tarazona trabajahndo con un companero de club en construccion de conej eras.
    - CCBR, Aragua, Carpentry, Prints: 7 (Box 9, Folder 166)
      77. Home improvement, through the adaptation of materials and means at hand, is being taught to nurses' aides of the state of Aragua in a four-week course offered by home economists of the Consejo de Bienstar Rural in Maracay. Part of the course offered the young women, all employs of rural health units in Aragua, concerns the construction of rudimentary furniture from packing crates, etc. 78. Home improvement, through the adaptation of materials and means at hand, is being taught to nurses' aides of the state of Aragua in a four-week course offered by home economists of the Consejo de Bienstar Rural in Maracay. Part of the course offered the young women, all employs of rural health units in Aragua, concerns the construction of rudimentary furniture from packing crates etc. 79. Learning to wield a saw in a class for constructing rudimentary furniture is only one part of the extensive home improvement course, offered to nurses' aides of the Aragua State Health Service by home economists of the Consejo de Bienstar Rural. The girls also are taught sewing and the adaptation of feed sacks and other readily available materials to the family clothing needs; cooking and preserving of food and arrangement of proper diets and community organization, including the founding of women's and girl's clubs. 80. Construction of useful household objects from waste material-the two girls are painting a garbage container made from a discarded oil tin-and household furniture from scrap lumber long has been a part of the CBR home demonstration program. The young staff of the "Cacique Charaima" school want to incorporate it in their community education program and secured the aid of CBR home demonstration training director Elba Velez to establish such a course. 81. CBR home demonstration training director, Elba Velez, nails metal slats in place on a bed built by women of the Palo Negro community as one of the initial projects in the carpentry course Miss Velez helped initiate at the experimental school "Cacique Charaima". 82. No caption. 83. No caption.
    - CBR, Aragua, Gardening, Prints: 1 (Box 9, Folder 167)
      84. School children cultivate fruit and vegetable gardens to add to the CBR-initiated school luncheons.
    - CBR, Aragua, Schools, Prints: 4 (Box 9, Folder 168)
      85. The classroom is sufficiently roomy and properly illuminated at the Guanarito rural school in Aragua. 86. A big yellow bus for those children who attend school from neighboring communities. Other youngsters live in Palo Negro, a rural village in the state of Aragua. Adults receive the same combination of formal and vocational education at night as is offered their children during the day. 87. Quarters in the Macuayita school in Aragua are crowded and unsanitary, and facilities are critically limited. However, the order in which the pitiful one-room plant is kept indicates that the teacher is doing her utmost. 88. This school at El Concejo in Aragua is held in the former hacienda house of a property which reverted to the state. The fine old trees and garden are unusual adornment for the children's playground.
    - CBR, Barinas, Agriculture, Prints: 1 (Box 9, Folder 169)
      1. In a CBR test field, the results of fertilizing a corn patch are dramatically demonstrated; the fertilized crop at right is more than twice the size of the unfertilized crop.
    - CBR, Barinas, Carpentry, Prints: 8 (Box 9, Folder 170)
      2. Women of Barinas construct toys in provisional home shops under supervision of CBR home demonstration staff. They also made rudimentary furniture. 3. This Barinas baby is enjoying one of the first strong, safe cribs to appear in the neighborhood where he lives. It was built by his mother from scrap lumber with CBR supervision. Note the mosquito bar suspended above the crib. 4. Mother and child try out the table and chairs which the former constructed in a carpentry class offered by CBR home demonstration workers in Barinas. 5. Women of Barinas add to their limited household furnishings by constructing simple furniture from scrap lumber with direction from the CBR home demonstration staff. These cabinets are especially useful in protecting the family food supply from insects and rodents. 6. Christmas 1953 was the gayest ever for the little rural community of Sabenta in Barinas. Parents constructed simple toys for their children in the carpentry shop at the CBR neighborhood center and distributed them at a Christmas party. 7. This little girl is delighted with the roller toy which her mother made in a CBR carpentry class at the neighborhood center in Sabaneta, rural community in the state of Barinas. 8. The CBR neighborhood center Christmas party in Sabaneta, Barinas, was a decided success. Guests are leaving, after refreshments and distribution of gifts, toys constructed in the carpentry shop at the center. 9. In this simple shop of the CBR neighborhood center at Sabaneta, state of Barinas, members of the community construct simple furniture and other domestic needs. The man in the photo is at work on one of the toys distributed to children of the community at Christmas.
    - CBR, Barinas, Community Center - Caja de Agua, Prints: 2 (Box 9, Folder 171)
      10. Once the governor has laid the corner stone, work proceeds rapidly on the Caja de Agua neighborhood center building. 11. The governor of the state of Barinas (left with child), director of the Barinas Health Unit (center) and Mrs. Lilian Fernandez, CBR home demonstration director for the region (right), followed by the people of the Caja de Agua community, approach the site of the new neighborhood center to be built from materials contributed by the state and organized by CBR.
    - CBR, Barinas, Crafts, Prints: 3 (Box 9, Folder 172)
      12. CBR home demonstration agent Graciela Escalona gives sewing course to Barinas women and girls. 13. CBR home demonstration director Lilian Fernandez directs activities of a girls' Home Economics Club in Barinas. 14. Barinas women and girls learn to make cloth toys under the supervision of a home demonstration staff.
    - CBR, Barinas, Gardening, Prints: 6 (Box 9, Folder 173)
      15. This Barinas woman has quite an onion crop. Hers is among several family garden projects supervised by CBR. 16. Children and grown-ups share in the chores of the community garden in the school yard of the Barinas community of Obispo. There was a severe shortage of fresh fruit and vegetables in Barinas before CVR undertook its gardening campaign. The only such foodstuff available was trucked in from the Andes and the prices were prohibitive to the average consumer. 17. CBR home demonstration workers instruct Barinas residents in the use of a garden tractor as part of a state-wide home gardening campaign. Surveys by Mrs. Lilian Fernandez, the home economics program supervisor, revealed that the average low income diet was dangerously deficient in necessary proteins, vitamins and minerals. Here school children of the Barinas mountain community of Barinitas are shown at work in one of the community gardens established in the state. 18. The state of Barinas was without home grown fresh vegetables and imported ones were prohibitively expensive until the Consejo de Bienstar Rural undertook a state-wide home gardening campaign. Surveys by Mrs. Lilian Fernandez, the home economics program supervisor, revealed that the average low income diet was dangerously deficient in necessary proteins, vitamins and minerals. Here school children of the Barinas mountain community of Barinitas are shown at work in one of the community gardens established in the state. 19. This Barinas family garden is yielding a good eggplant crop. Seed was distributed through CBR; and CBR home demonstration agents and extension workers advised the novice gardeners. 20. Parents and children work side by side in the community garden, sponsored by CBR in Barinitas, Barinas.
    - CBR, Barinas, Home Improvement, Prints: 5 (Box 9, Folder 174)
      21. Several thatched roofs have given way to the CBR campaign. The roof-raising drive also has led to further improvements in many of the dwellings. 22. Barinas is a capital with the largest population in the state, yet most of the homes are roofed in straw. CBR home demonstration director, Mrs. Lilian Fernandez, with government approval, has been waging a steady and prolonged campaign for replacing this unsanitary and dangerous roofing. 23. This sanitary latrine was constructed as a demonstration project by the Barinas CBR home demonstration staff. Thereafter, others were built on private initiative with CBR supervision. The government provided the necessary cement. 24. Here is a new bridge over the Bocono River, linking the southwest with the rest of the nation. Former bridges over this treacherous stream, which swells greatly during the rainy season, have washed out, leaving southwest Barinas isolated. 25. A typical rural dwelling in the Guanare-Barinas region.
    - CBR, Barinas, Miscellaneous, Prints: 3 (Box 9, Folder 175)
      26. This Barinas woman is extracting juices from sugar cane in the same manner as her forebears. 27. Family and friends join in the task of twisting the cane; the youngsters like to suck the sweet, crushed stalks. 28. No caption.
    - CBR, Barinas, Nutrition, Prints: 4 (Box 9, Folder 176)
      29. Fruit salad delights the children of Sabaneta at the Christmas party given in the CBR neighborhood center. 30. Before the construction of the new Caja de Agua neighborhood center, milk and cereal were served daily to pre-school age children of the Barinas area in a provisional center supplied from a CBR mobile unit. 31. On the day he laid the corner stone for the new Caja de Agua neighborhood center, the governor visited the provisional center where milk, buns, and bananas brought by the CBR mobile unit were served to pre-school age children. 32. The governor of the state of Barinas lays the corner stone for the new building which will serve as a neighborhood center and milk station for the impoverished Caja de Agua section of the city. Mrs. Lilian Fernandez, CBR home demonstration director for the Barinas area, is far right.
    - CBR, Carabobo, Agriculture, Prints: 33 (Box 9, Folder 177)